A Guide to the Anna Burton Ellett Collection, 1751-1932
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Anna Burton Ellett Collection, 1751-1932
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1974-010
0.3 cu. ft. 1 box; 1 oversize folder
Materials relating to early residents of Southwest Virginia (particularly James Patton, William Preston, and John Preston) and the commemoration of the 200th anniversary of George Washington's birth in 1932, all collected by Anna Burton Ellett, a Blacksburg resident and active member of the Daughters of the American Revolution and the Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities.
Ellett, Anna Burton
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Biographical Note
Anna Burton Ellett, daughter of Henry W. and Anna Elizabeth Bass Burton, was born in Lynchburg, Virginia on March 5, 1886. Following the early death of her mother, she spent her childhood at the home of her great uncle, James A. Walker, of Rockbridge County, Virginia. She later attended high school in Durham, North Carolina, and graduated from Trinity College in 1906. In 1918, she accepted a position with the Virginia Extension Service in Blacksburg, where she met and married Walter Beal Ellett, head of Virginia Tech's Department of Agricultural Chemistry. She was an active member of both the Daughters of the American Revolution and the Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities. Anna Burton Ellett died in Shawsville, Virginia on April 28, 1974.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains materials acquired by Anna Burton Ellett, a resident of Blacksburg, Virginia, through her interest in local and United States history. The collection includes correspondence, legal documents, and military records from Southwest Virginia as well as printed materials relating to the bicentennial commemoration of the 1732 birth of President George Washington.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in two series:
Series I. Southwest Virginia Historical Documents, 1751-1841. This series contains materials acquired by Ellett through her interest in local history. The documents focus largely on the Patton and Preston families, particularly James Patton, William Preston, and John Preston. Included are correspondence and legal documents, as well as pay records and rosters of John Preston's company of local volunteer militia. The series also contains a few pieces from other sources, including a justice of the peace certification for Samuel D. King, signed by Daniel Webster; a list of goods apparently stolen from Capt. Adam Levinson; and a survey map apparently showing streams in present-day Montgomery County, Virginia.
Series II. Washington Bicentennial Celebration, 1931-1932. This series contains printed materials produced--mostly by the George Washington Bicentennial Commission--to guide local organizations in commemorating the 200th anniversary of Washington's birth. Included are essays, programs, scripts, music, and promotional materials.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Separated Materials
The following items were removed from the collection and cataloged for the Rare Book Collection:
Colonial gardens: the landscape architecture of George Washington's time. Washington, D.C.: United States George Washington Bicentennial Commission, [1932]. SB466 U6 A6 c.2 Large Spec
Ellett, W. B. "Sugar Beets in Virginia." Circular (Virginia Agricultural Experiment Station), no. 1. LD5655 A5231 C45 no. 1 VPI Spec
Index Terms
Subjects:
Blacksburg (Va.); Local/Regional History and Appalachian South; Montgomery County (Va.)
Contents List
- Series I. Southwest Virginia Historical Documents, 1754-1841
  - James Patton, 1754-1797, [see also Oversize Materials] (Box-folder 1-1)
    - John Adams / Michael Kinder bond, 1754
    - Patton's estate - Elijah Isaac bond, 1763
    - Patton's estate - Hugh Mares account (Joseph Cloyd and John Leyburn, arbitrators), 1797
  - William Preston, 1769-1783, [see also Oversize Materials] (Box-folder 1-2)
    - Botetourt County tax itemization and receipt, 1769
    - Letter from J. Thompson, 1774
    - Letter from George Skillern, 1779
    - Letter from John Preston, 1782
    - Letter from [Jonathan Taylor?], 1783
  - John Preston, 1814-1825, [see also Oversize Materials] (Box-folder 1-3)
    - Letter from Daniel Howe, 1814
    - Letter from David French, 1817
    - Letter from George Hancock, 1825
  - General Documents, 1841, n.d., [see also Oversize Materials] (Box-folder 1-4)
    - Samuel D. King justice of the peace certification (signed by Daniel Webster), 1841
    - Notes on Thomas and Robert Rutherford's Ohio River land parcels, n.d.
    - "An account of what goods the [Indians robbed?] from Capt. Adam Levinson," n.d.
    - Metes and bounds of two surveys, n.d.
    - Masonic speech, n.d.
- Series II. George Washington Bicentennial Celebration, 1931-1932, n.d.
  - "Programs and Papers Portraying the Personality, Character, and Achievements of George Washington," 1931, [2 copies] (Box-folder 1-5)
  - Pageants and plays, 1931-1932, n.d. (Box-folder 1-6)
  - Music, 1931-1932, n.d. (Box-folder 1-7)
  - Promotional materials, 1932, n.d., [see also Oversize Materials]
- Oversize Materials, 1751-1792, n.d. (Oversize 1)
  - Roll of Captain [John] Preston's company of volunteer militia, 1792
  - Monthly reports of Captain [John] Preston's company of volunteer militia, 1792, [4 items]
  - Roll of Lieutenant [Robert] Crockett's detachment of Capt. Preston's company, [1792?]
  - Pay record for scouts in John Preston's volunteer militia company, 1792
  - Land indenture: James Patton to John Petersally (Augusta County, Virginia), 1751
  - Land indenture: George Robinson to Joseph McDonald (Augusta County, Virginia), 1755
  - Land indenture: Joseph and Elizabeth McDonald to William Preston (Augusta County, Virginia), 1763
  - Unidentified map showing Walkers Little Creek, Peak Creek, Cave Creek, Stoney Fork, and others, n.d.
  - George Washington Bicentennial Commission clip sheet, [1932]